Finding Aid for the Albert Zugsmith Papers LSC.1044
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert Zugsmith papers
1950-1968
UCLA Library Special Collections
Zugsmith, Albert.
LSC.1044
5.5 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
Collection of screenplays, treatments and related material.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Albert Zugsmith, 1968-1969.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9936493903606533
Biography
Albert Zugsmith's Opium Dreams.
Scope and Content
Contains 17 shooting scripts, 19 treatments, outlines etc., miscellaneous advertising material, and a photo or two of Zugsmith.
Film scripts.; Zugsmith, Albert.
- Production files
  - Adam & Eve by George Beck., no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Director's copy of script. Signed by AZ.
  - Back to Jerusalem by Uri Oren (outline for film scripts)., no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Battle for Earth (The) - Story line by Arthur Orloff., 1956 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Be My Guest by Conrad Hilton - Outline by Elaine St. Johns., no date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bear by the Tail by Samuel Taylor., no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bird in the Sky - Original screenplay by Richard Valen., no date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boy in the Bottle (The) by Bert I. Gordon., no date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boy in the Bottle (The) by Bert I. Gordon., no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Call House Madam - Screenplay by Fred De Gorder., no date (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "Property of: Herts-Lion International Corp., 845 No. Seward, Los Angeles, Calif."
  - Carnival Kid (The) by Gus Edson - Second draft., 1961 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Producer's copy signed by AZ.
  - Carnival Kid (The) by Gus Edson - Second draft [another copy]., 1961 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Producer's copy, signed by AZ.
  - Carnival Kid (The) - Screenplay by Sid Kuller and Gus Edson - Revised final draft., 1961 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Producer's copy, signed. With illustration "Shana in the act of 'the cut off head.'"
  - Carnival Kid (The) - Screenplay by Sid Kuller and Gus Edson - Revised final draft., no date (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Signed by AZ. With illustration, "Shana in the act of 'the cut off head.'" Also signed by AZ.
  - Cast the First Stone - Roger Lewis treatment., no date (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Garrick Films.
  - Catch Those Kidnappers! by Colin Drake., no date (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Other suggested titles "Three Flies in the Soup", "A Kid on Their Hands".
  - Chinese Room (The) by Vivian Connell - Screenplay by Albert Zugsmith., 1966 June 27 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Cover sheet signed by Albert Zugsmith.
  - Chinese Room (The) - First draft screenplay by Albert Zugsmith based on the great modern English classic., 1966 May 21 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    "Original director's-writer's signed copy", signed by AZ on cover.
  - Classified Tour (A) by George Jessel - Memo from George Jessel, [overview] and opening sequence., no date (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cobblestone Range (The) by George Van Marter., 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Part of the title page has been cut away. Reg. WGA-W. With summary from Universal-International Pictures Story Department.
  - Confessions of an Opium Eater by Robert Smith - [Based on the writings of Thomas de Quincey]., no date (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Director's copy, signed by AZ on first page. With 2 page memo from AZ re the story treatment by Smith.
  - Crocodile Kiss (The) - Treatment by Robert Hill., 1956 February 14 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Producer's copy, signed by AZ on cover.
  - Cry Hard, Cry Fast - Final screenplay by Robert Hill., 1956 August (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cry Violence - Treatment synopsis by Lewis Clay., 1954 November (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Signed by AZ on cover. With one page of summary, signed by AZ, dated 1955 January 26. "Screenplay by Alfred Hayes, adapted by Herbert Kline from the novel "Let Me Breathe Thunder" by William Attaway.
  - Daring and the Damned (The) - Original screenplay by Fred Freiberger., no date (Box 2, Folder 9)
    "Based on an idea by John Rapp and Lester White."
  - Devil's Own (The) by Beda Brown., no date (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Story sent to AZ?
  - Divine Comedy - Film-story by Marino Girolami., no date (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Thermofax copy.
  - Dondi Goes Native in Brooklyn - Treatment outline by Gus Edson., 1960 August 18 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Cover signed by AZ.
  - Dondi Goes Native in Brooklyn - Treatment outline by Gus Edson., 1960 August 18 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Signed by AZ on cover. With one page of notes by E. Ziegler.
  - Dondi Goes to the Moon by Gus Edson., 1960 November 15 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Signed by AZ on cover.
  - Don't Talk To Me About Women by Victor Canning., no date (Box 2, Folder 15)
    From H.N. Swanson, Inc. Thermofax copy.
  - Dondi - Production reports., 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Final billing sheet and daily production and progress reports. With photograph taken on the set.
  - I Am Your Mirror by Herbert Tjadens., no date (Box 3, Folder 2)
    European Film Agency.
  - Incredible Sex Revolution (The) - Portions of script, notes, rewrites., no date (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Man in Tower (The) by John Kafka., no date (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Part of the title page has been cut away.
  - Mr. Acrobat [by] George Zuckerman., no date (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mr. Acrobat [by] George Zuckerman., 1956 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oh, you doctor! - Created and written by Phillip Shuken., no date (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Title on first page of screenplay is "Oh, You Nurse."
  - Private Lives of Adam and Eve (The) - Production budget., 1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Produced and directed by Albert Zugsmith. Signed by AZ on summary page.
  - Pylon [by George Zuckerman] - Production budget., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Produced by Albert Zugsmith. Signed by AZ on summary page.
  - Robinson 1964 - Original story by Max Colpet and Lotar Olias., 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - When Strangers Meet - Screenplay by Michael Elkins and Fr. Habeck., no date (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Signed by AZ on title page. "Based upon the best-seller by Robert Bloomfield."
  - Written on the Wind - Production budget., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Produced by Albert Zugsmith. Signed on summary sheet by AZ.
  - Fabulous Scoundrel (The) - [Changes], memo, character sketches., 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Memo, dated 7 December 1955, re outline of revisions, signed by AZ on page 1.
  - Fabulous Scoundrel (The) - Treatment by Richard Alan Simmons., 1955 October (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Family Affair - [Comments by Sidney Phillips]., 1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Two copies of letter addressed to Kenneth MacKenna.
  - Fantastic Little Girl (The) - Step outline by Richard Matheson., 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Produced by Albert Zugsmith. Signed by AZ on cover and title page.
  - Fatty (The Roscoe "Fatty" Arbuckle story) by Harry Essex., no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
    With Famous Artists Corporation cover.
  - Female on the Beach - [cover title] Besieged Heart by Robert Hill., [1955] (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Produced by Albert Zugsmith. Signed by AZ on title page.
  - First Man (The) - A motion picture project by Richard Tregaskis and Hannibal Coons., 1960 June 29 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Colonial Film Productions cover.
  - Glory of God (The) by Frank H. Stuckert., no date (Box 4, Folder 8)
    The pages are laminated.
  - Gulliver's Travels by Jonathan Swift, adapted story line by Albert & Ruth Zugsmith., no date (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Two pages, signed by Albert Zugsmith and Ruth Zugsmith. For American Pictures Corp.
  - Gyp the Blood by Walter Winchell., no date (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Heads or Tails - A treatment for a comedy with improvised dialogues written by Ika Panajotovic., no date (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Her Bed of Roses - Synopsis [for] screenplay by Albert Zugsmith, based on Krafft- Ebing's Psychopathia Sexualis., no date (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Signed by AZ on page 1.
  - Here Come the Pigeons by Jack Sher and Arthur Ross - Screen treatment., [1955] (Box 4, Folder 13)
    With memo from Universal-International Pictures Story Department. Rosenberg-Coryell Agency cover.
  - Hooker (The) by Tom Hennesy and Roul Haig., no date (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Registered: Screen Writers' Guild No. 77541.
  - Hot Rice., no date (Box 4, Folder 15)
    "A contemporary, swinging version of Gilbert & Sullivan's Mikado."
  - House Party - A treatment synopsis by Lewis Clay., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Signed by AZ on the cover. "Based on the novel The Great Snow by Henry Morton Robinson." Universal-International Pictures cover.
  - House Party - First draft screenplay by Robert Hill., 1955 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Signed by AZ on the cover. Universal-International Pictures cover.
  - How Foul My Love? - A treatment for the screen by Richard Steger., no date (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - How To Break Into the Movies by Albert Zugsmith., no date (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Signed by AZ on title page.
  - Human Guinea Pigs or The Big Gamble., no date (Box 4, Folder 20)
    [Story outline]. Signed by AZ on page 1.
  - Id (The) by Bert I. Gordon., no date (Box 4, Folder 21)
    [Story outline].
  - In the Wrong Rain - Novel by Robert Kirsch, submitted by Hal Landers of Jaffe Agency., no date (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Two page outline, signed "Bob" on page 2.
  - Immortal (The) by Walter Ross - Outline and synopsis by Edward Hogan., 1957 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Cover note: "#16, file copy."
  - Immortal (The) - An approach by Albert Zugsmith., 1959 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    With note from Sol C. Siegel, Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Pictures, 1959 June 29. Signed by AZ on cover.
  - Isle of Widows (The) - German script [by] Wolf Neumeister., no date (Box 5, Folder 1)
    "A film by Iwe Ribic."
  - Last Party (The) by Jesse Lasky Jr. and Barney Slater., no date (Box 5, Folder 2)
    MCA Story Department cover.
  - License to Steal (A) by Jimmy Starr - Synopsis., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Live a Little by Jermit Kahn., no date (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lonesome Gal - An original step-outline by Jean King Rousseau., 1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lonesome Husband [by Phyllis Duganne] - Step-outline by Oscar Brodney., 1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    With published story from The Saturday Evening Post (October 2, 1954), memo from AZ to Edward Muhl, James Pratt, etc. Signed by AZ on cover.
  - Love Has No Age by Frederick Stephani., no date (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Part of the cover has been cut away.
  - Lullilongo (A musical comedy outline) by Colin Drake., no date (Box 5, Folder 8)
    "Registered with S.A.C.D."
  - Man a Day (A) - Idea and treatment by Luciana Corda [&] Ettore M. Margadonna., no date (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Man and Boy by Harry Essex and John Fante., no date (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Ingo Preminger Agency cover.
  - Man Crazy - An original story by Katheriene & Dale Eunson., no date (Box 5, Folder 11)
    William Shiffrin Agency cover.
  - Man Who Sold the Eiffel Tower (The) - Screenplay by Nick Gorski and Gae Carrell., no date (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Based on the book … by James F. Johnson and Floyd Miller. Part of the cover and title page have been cut away.
  - Mayday - proposed television series .. [by] Christy Walsh., 1961 July 20 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Mike Fink, King of the River / Mike Fink Returns Home - pilot film, second and final revision - Story by Jeff York, screenplay by James Landis and Jeff York., no date (Box 5, Folder 14)
    "Property of: Tee Dee Productions."
  - Miracle of the Fishes (The) - A story idea for Rock Hudson or Billy Graham by Robert Smith., no date (Box 5, Folder 15)
    See also: The Velvet Lash.
  - Money, Women and Dreams (formerly Round-Up) by Robert Blees and Harry Essex., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Signed by AZ on title page. With 2 copies of memo to AZ from Harry Essex and Robert Blees, 1955 March 30. Ingo Preminger Agency cover.
  - Morianerna - press kit(?)., no date (Box 5, Folder 17)
    "Script file." A film directed by Arne Matsson, film scenario by Arne Matsson and Per Wahlï.
  - Movie Star, American Style or How I Fell in Love with LSD - Screenplay by Albert Zugsmith & Graham Lee Mahin. Based on a story by Albert Zugsmith., no date (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Director's signed copy, signed by AZ on title page. Based on a story by Albert Zugsmith.
  - Movie Star, American Style - First draft screenplay by Albert Zugsmith and Graham Lee Mahin., no date (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Signed by AZ on cover. Alternate titles: Nymphet, Sappho 1970.
  - Number One - Step outline by Herbert Abbott Spiro., 1956 December 10 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Number One - Step outline by Herbert Abbott Spiro., 1956 December 10 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Producer's signed copy, signed by AZ on cover.
  - Nymphet - A treatment for the screen by Albert Zugsmith and Richard Steger., no date (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Signed by AZ on cover and title page.
  - Oh Georgie., no date (Box 6, Folder 6)
    General note
    [No author credit given.]
  - Oh, Nurse! - Created and written by Phillip Shuken., no date (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Date (Sept. 28, 1962) and Property of Desilu Productions, Inc. has been crossed out in red.
  - On the Run - Film script by Niels Karting (Helmut Weiss)., no date (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Our Sexual Revolution - Treatment Part I - The Wife Swappers., no date (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Writer and director's original copy, signed by AZ on cover. "A documentary drama by Albert Zugsmith."
  - Pawnbroker (The) or The Pawnbroker and the Lady by Herbert Abbott Spiro., 1956 December 13 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    "An idea for a screenplay based on the life and times of Arnold Rothstein."
  - Phantom gunslinger by Albert Zugsmith., no date (Box 6, Folder 11)
    "Signed writer-director copy" noted on cover. Title page is missing and part of page 1 has been cut away.
  - Piccola Guida (La) - Screenplay by Adam LaZarre., no date (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Part of the title page has been cut away. "From an original idea by: Glenn Rose and Robert Alda."
  - Pie In Your Eye by L. Glass and Rome Cowgill., no date (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Platinum High School - Step Outline by Robert Smith., 1959 March 20 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Signed by AZ on the cover. Notes in red ink on back cover.
  - Platinum High School - Revised outline by Robert Smith., 1959 April 1 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Psychopathia Sexualis - Screen treatment by Albert Zugsmith., no date (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Signed by AZ on cover. Also known as "Krafft-Ebing's Psychopathia Sexualis."
  - Psychopathia Sexualis - A film by Albert Zugsmith. Also known as "On Her Bed of Roses.", 1965 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    "Writer-director working signed copy with notes and changes [by] Albert Zugsmith."
  - Rip Van Winkle in the 21st Century (Jack H. Harris') - Story and screenplay by Marion Hargrove, based on the story by Washington Irving., 1960 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Rope of Flesh - Screenplay by Raymond Friday Locke and W.E. Sprague. Based on the novel "Streets Paved with Gold" by Friday Locke., 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Dialogue script. Copyright 1965, Delta Films, Inc.
  - Running Target - Original story and screenplay by Derek Ford., no date (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Saddle-Bum by Lawrence Roman., no date (Box 7, Folder 3)
    [Outline].
  - Sappho by Albert Zugsmith. Alternate title: Baby Sex., 1968 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Signed by AZ on cover. With a few holograph annotations.
  - Sappho, Tell It As It Is! by Albert Zugsmith., 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Signed by AZ on cover. Registered: Writers' Guild of America. With some holograph annotations.'
  - Sappho 1968 [by Albert Zugsmith]. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Part of the cover and first page have been cut away.
  - Sappho 1968 [by Albert Zugsmith]. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Shadow of the Noose by John and Ward Hawkins., 1955 October 19 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Synopsis by Kay Lenard. With note, "Some merit but? Z".
  - Shock Treatment., no date (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Thermofax copy. "With note: Please return to Albert Zugsmith …"
  - Shock Treatment. [This version titled "Tokyo"]., no date (Box 7, Folder 10)
    With note, "Please return to Albert Zugsmith."
  - Sinners in Pink., no date (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Sleep, Sleep, Pussycat by William Maron., 1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - South of the Sun - Treatment., 1954 September 23 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Signed by AZ on cover. "Property of Universal-International Pictures."
  - Stranger at Clipper Bay - First draft screenplay by George Zuckerman., 1954 October 25 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Stranger at Clipper Bay (formerly Miracle of the Fishes) - first draft screenplay by George Zuckerman., 1954 October 30 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Strangers on the Shore by Douglas Kiker [summary]., no date (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Reader: Evelyn Humphrey.
  - Subject: Taboo [by] Lawrence Roman., 1958 March 30 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Signed by AZ on the cover.
  - Survey: The Teen-Agers by Albert Zugsmith - treatment., 1959 October 12 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Signed by AZ on title page. "Property of Universal-International Pictures."
  - Survey: The Teen-Agers by Albert Zugsmith - treatment., 1959 October 12 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - T.J. - Screenplay by Bob Wehling, story by Doug Wilson., no date (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Representation by H.N. Swanson Agency. SWG No. 64023.
  - Third of a Man [by Robert Lewin]., 1957 May 20 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Memo and summary from Universal-International Pictures Story Department, read by Frank Thompson, submitted by Department Coverage (Zugsmith).
  - This Rebel Generation [by] Lewis Meltzer., 1959 July 17 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Signed by AZ on cover. Release title: The Beat Generation?
  - Time for Fear (A) - A novel by Roderick MacLeish., no date (Box 8, Folder 4)
    "The Real Estate Man" crossed out on title page. Manuscript note on preliminary page "To be published by Viking Press." With Famous Artists Associates, Inc. cover.
  - Town (The) [by] William Faulkner., 1957 March 26 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Memo and summary by Universal-International Pictures Story Department. Read by Dick Whittle, submitted by New York (Harold Ober Associates).
  - Trunk to Cairo - Original story by M. Golan and M. Kagan, screenplay by Marc Behm., no date (Box 8, Folder 6)
    "Property of: Noah Films, Ltd., 68 Pinsker St., Tel Aviv, Israel."
  - Two Algerian Knights [by John Carroll?]., no date (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Underdog by W.R. Burnett., no date (Box 8, Folder 8)
    From H.N. Swanson, Inc.
  - Velvet Lash (The) - First draft screenplay by John Fante., 1955 March 30 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Signed by AZ on cover. Formerly titled: Miracle of the Fishes.
  - Vickie - Original idea created and written by Roger Leonard., no date (Box 8, Folder 10)
    "A treatment for the pilot of a proposed half-hour T-V Series." Rainbow Productions.
  - Voyage to Lilliput (A) - First draft screenplay by Richard Matheson., 1956 November 12 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Signed by AZ on cover. Original screen story by Richard Matheson and Albert Zugsmith, based upon a novel by Jonathan Swift.
  - Walk by the Sea - First draft, revised, original story and screenplay by Ned W. Miller., 1962 July 25 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Part of the cover and title page have been cut away. Registered: Screen Writers Guild.
  - War Toys - First draft screenplay by Franc Arnold and Montgomery Pittman from the novel "Hunger Valley" by Edward S. Fox., 1967 November 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Award Productions, Inc.
  - Wife for George (A) - Story and screenplay by Rutherford Montgomery., 1963 April 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Wife for George (A) - Story and screenplay by Rutherford Montgomery., 1963 April 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Signed by AZ on page 1. Thermofax copy.
  - Wolf Girl of India by Frank H. Stuckert - synopsis., no date (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Registered: Writers Guild of America. Pages are laminated.
  - Wolf Girl of India by Frank H. Stuckert - synopsis., no date (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Another copy. Registered: Writers Guild of America. The pages are laminated.
  - Year of the Cricket - An original screenplay by John Loring and Mary Murray., no date (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Young Giants (The), Moment of Decision - First draft screenplay by Tom Waldman & Frank Waldman., no date (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Jack Arnold - photograph inscribed "To Zug -- forever grateful …", 1957 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Copyright Universal Pictures Company, Inc.
  - Unidentified production photograph - "Ralph Black" on verso., no date (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Dondi bumper sticker - publicity material., no date (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - High School Confidential (?) - photos of Mamie Van Doren and Albert Zugsmith [contact sheet]., no date (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Dondi - [poster]., no date (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Platinum High School - [poster], signed by Albert Zugsmith., no date (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Adam and Eve [by] Stanley Roberts, 1957 December 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Dondi Goes Native in Brooklyn by Gus Edson, 1960 August 18 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Signed by AZ on front cover.
  - Dondi Goes to the Moon by Gus Edson, 1960 November 15 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Incredible Sex Revolution (The) - Screenplay by Robert Hill, no date. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Signed by AZ on the title page. With manuscript annotations in an unidentifed
  - Pylon (William Faulkner's) - First draft screenplay by George Zuckerman., 1956 May 21. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Signed by AZ on the title page.
  - Roughing It - The Fabulous Feud - Written by John Fange and Edmund Morris., no date. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Registered with: Writers Guild of American West, Inc. #71125
- Personal files
  - [Cartoon] - inscribed "For my friend, Al Zugsmith-- Long may he pour! Gus Edson.", no date (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Box 10 is an oversize flat box, 15 x 19".